Here are a few examples of how risk
tolerance can drive decision making for organizations.
An organization is required to build a bid package to gain a contract.
The time and effort of personnel building a
bid package will cost the organization $10,000.
If the organization wins the contract, the contract pays $2
million.
The organization decides to accept the risk of losing the cost of
the bid package because the benefit of winning the contract is appealing,
the risk of losing the bid and the cost of
building the bid package is within the organization's risk threshold.
A trauma center has three critical care units
where patients are provided life sustaining services,
breathing and heart activity
through the use of machines,
inactivity of these machines could mean that people will die.
The trauma center has zero tolerance for power failure.
So creates redundancy,
emergency power supplies through the use of multiple utility power providers,
battery backup and multiple generators with secure fuel supplies and solid
contracts with fuel providers to deliver
additional fuel during emergency situations.
Liza and Chris think they can build a business that is profitable and enjoyable.
They decide to quit their jobs and start the business together.
They tolerate the risk that their business might
fail because the reward they perceive is significant.